Guide to the Medieval manuscript fragments, [ca. 800-ca. 1800]
Medieval manuscript fragments
- Three bindings strips from an unidentified manuscript., Early thirteenth century.; Size: 1: 290 x 42 mm. 2: 144 x 49 mm. 3: 144 x 34 mm. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Description: Three binding strips in a Textualis Formata (Quadratus) script. Two of the strips are taken from the edge of the text block and feature alternate blue and red initials with decorative penwork. All three fragments are broken in two and have been taped back together.
  Provenance: Formerly p.53 (1-3).
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_016_001.jpg (1a); CornellMedMS_016_002.jpg (1b); CornellMedMS_016_004.jpg (2a); CornellMedMS_016_003.jpg (2b); CornellMedMS_016_005.jpg (3a); CornellMedMS_016_006.jpg (3b).
- Decorated leaf from a Psalter, probably from Northern France., Late thirteenth century.; Size: 177 x 130 mm (151 x 89 mm). (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Description: Psalms written in Latin in a Textualis Formata (Quadratus) script on parchment. Highly decorated Lombard capitals in red and blue ink with gold leaf. Decorated initial “O” with image of seated prophet holding book inside. Numerous marginalia and fillers including a man, dogs, a deer, and other beasts.
  Provenance: Lost description by Raegan Russell, 10th May 1999. Formerly Ferrini no. 60.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_003_001.jpg (a), CornellMedMS_003_002.jpg (b).
- Leaf from Antiphonal with decorated initial “E” with blue wolves from Italy., Last quarter of the thirteenth century, ca. 1280.; Size: 474 x 351 mm (362 x 255 mm). Four staves: 27.8 mm. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Northern Textualis Formata script. Seven four line staves in red with gothic script and square musical notation. Alternate red and blue initials with some red rubrication. The verso contains a historiated initial (measuring 11 x 10cm) which illustrates the Responsory, “Ecce ego mitto vos ut oves in medio luporum” (“Behold, I send you forth as sheep in the midst of wolves”).
  Provenance: Formerly Broadside bb13; folder 18.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_060_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_060_002.jpg (b).
- Fragment from a codex by Justinian, with historiated initials. From southern France., Ca. 1280.; Size: 164 x 35 mm. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Gothic script. Remains of a partial column of text and surrounding gloss on both recto and verso. Decoration: a small historiated initial of a woman's head in a blue cloak (recto); a human with an animal head (verso). Both initials on colored grounds, largely blue, with gold drops on gesso and marginal extensions.
- Framed document from Germany featuring wax seal of female abbess., Dated 1288.; Size: 72/78 x 191 mm (63 x 183 mm). (Mapcase-folder 1)
  Description: Legal document on parchment featuring seal of abbess Jutta appended to the bottom of the document. Jutta was mother superior and administrator of the cloister of St. Bonifatius in Freckenhorst from 1272-98. Partial transcription reads: “Jutta, dei gratia abbatissa in [Freckenhorst, Nordrhein-Westfalen, Germany], universis visuris presentia protestamus, quod cum Johannes dictus de Berg et sui coheredes haberent ex bonis nostris [name of a tract of land owned by the abbey, Elsendorf?] que colit Rodolphus, XXXII denarius salvendos eisdem dominica ante ascentionem Domini… pensionem annuatim ab incolis bonorum nostrorum in dicta quantitate et in termino memorato… in cujius rei testimonium presens scriptum sigilo nostro fecimus communiri… Datum anno Domini MCC LXXX octavo (1288), feria secunda Mathie apostoli”.
  Provenance: Acquired in 2013 by Laurent Ferri.
- Leaf from a Breviary with decorative “C” initial., Late thirteenth to early fourteenth century.; Size: 239 x 172 mm (178 x 120 mm). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in an angular Textualis Formata (Textus Quadratus) script with 18 lines of text. Commences “In vigilia sancti Andree apostolo” and ends, “da nobis in eterna beatitudine de eorum societate gaudere. Per…”. Rubricated in red ink. Smaller initials in red and blue with pen flourishes. Large blue decorative initial “C” enclosing entwined ivy rinceaux on gold ground and enframed by a red field decorated with white filigree. Ivy branches spring from a vertical staff in left margin.
  Provenance: Formerly Calkins, no. 6; De Ricci, II, p. 1237; folder 08.
- Fragment in Greek from Gregory of Nicomedia, Sermo in S. Mariam assistentem cruci, probably from a homiliary., Thirteenth or fourteenth century.; Size: 338 x 265 mm. (Mapcase Mapcase, Folder 1 bis (folio 1))
  Description: Single folio on vellum. Ruled in dry-point, the text hanging from the upper line rather than written on the lower one. Double columns, 27 lines. Undecorated and unfoliated. Script: no use of iota subscript; use of nomina sacra.
  Provenance: Acquired by Laurent Ferri, September 2018.
- Fragment in Greek from the Gospel of Matthew 21:1-19, describing the entrance of Jesus into Jerusalem., Twelfth or thirteenth century.; Size: 263 x 201 mm (justification, 186 mm x 125 mm). (Mapcase Mapcase, Folder 1 bis (folio 2))
  Description: Single folio on vellum. Ruled in dry-point. Single column, 24 lines. Decoration: chapter numbering in margins and rubrics in carmine throughout the text, especially on the verso. Script: no evidence of iota subscript, but use of nomina sacra and some endings in abbreviated form. Text with some explication.
- Two mutilated bifolia from an inset gloss textbook from Italy., Thirteenth to fourteenth century.; Size: Fragment 1 (rubricated as XXXVI): 146/162 x 309/149 mm (122/84 x 136/104 mm incomplete). Fragment 2 (rubricated as XXXVII): 83/163 x 302/164 mm (140/113 x 144/114 mm incomplete). (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in an Italian Rotunda (Littera Bononiensis) script. Main text in two columns trimmed on both sides, with marginal commentary. Text is on the flesh side of both bifolia only. Blue and red initials, paraphs, pen flourishes, and rubrics.
  Provenance: Donated by Mrs Fleda Meyers. Lost description by Charles Reid, May 1986. Formerly h.27 (1-2).
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_017_003.jpg (1a); CornellMedMS_017_004.jpg (1b); CornellMedMS_017_001.jpg (2a); CornellMedMS_017_002.jpg (2b).
- Fragment from a glossed manuscript containing the Digests of Justinian, 36.1/3.1-2., Thirteenth to fourteenth century.; Size: 345 x 145 mm (345 x 134 mm incomplete). (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment with red paraphs in a Southern Textulis Libraria. Some fading of the main text, glossing is extremely faded (now almost illegible).
  Provenance: Lost description by Carol Neel, May 1978. Formerly k.29.
- Two leaves from a book, probably of canon law., Thirteenth to fourteenth century.; Size: Folio III: 299 x 205 mm (224 x 155 mm incomplete). Folio IIII: 257 x 203 mm (234 x 152 incomplete). (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in two columns in a Textualis Libraria scripts. Red paraphs and foliation: leaves are foliated as III and IIII (IV). Text is very faded and almost illegible.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 57.2
- Leaf from the Bible, Book of Zachariah., Thirteenth to fourteenth century.; Size: 282 x 191 mm (184 x 116 mm). (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Description: From the Book of Zachariah, written in Latin on parchment. Featuring a beautiful marginal illustration of an angel appearing to Zachariah with men on horseback. Decorated initials in red and blue ink.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 66.
- Thirteen mutilated bifolia and three fragments from a Latin manuscript., Late thirteenth to fourteenth century.; Size: Three fragments: 130 x 200 mm; 80 x 240 mm; 130 x 230 mm. Thirteen mutilated bifolia: 130 x 390 mm; 130 x 445 mm; 135 x 440 mm; 125 x 390 mm; 140 x 445 mm; 135 x 420 mm; 140 x 430 mm; 135 x 430 mm; 130 x 400 mm; 140 x 430 mm; 140 x 410 mm; 135 x 440 mm; 140 x 430 mm. Width of text block: 161mm. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Southern Textualis Libraria script in two columns. Text is badly faded and parchment partially worm eaten. Chapter numbers and occasional glosses in the margin.
  Provenance: Donated by Mrs Fleda Meyers. Lost description by Will Dickerson, n.d. Formerly l.50.
- One leaf from the Digests of Justinian, 27.1.45 - 27.3.2 from Northern Italy, probably Bologne., Fourteenth century.; Size: 329 x 244/232 mm (219 x 124 mm). (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Description: Written in Latin on Italian parchment in a Textualis Libraria script, in two columns with various glosses. Red and blue paraphs and initials with some decorative penwork. Red rubrics and marginal illustrations of a bird (recto) and a serpent (verso). The ink is a little faded on the flesh side.
  Provenance: Lost descriptions by Gina Paolai (1985) and Glen Starr (1975). Formerly g.26.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_078_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_078_002.jpg (b).
- One mutilated bifolium of a glossed Digest of Justinian: Liber XLV, from Bologna., Fourteenth century.; Size: 212 x 391/ 241 mm (182 x 134 mm). (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Bolognese script, with marginal glossing in a similar script. In brown ink with red and blue paraphs and initials. Transcription available in folder.
  Provenance: Formerly 19.1.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_025_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_025_001darker.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_025_002.jpg (b, c); CornellMedMS_025_002darker.jpg (b, c); CornellMedMS_025_003.jpg (d); CornellMedMS_025_003darker.jpg (d).
- Fragment from a glossed textbook from Italy, probably Bologne., Fourteenth century.; Size: 452 x 112 mm (342/307 x 72/42 mm incomplete). (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a compact Southern Textualis Libraria (Littera Bononiensis) script. Glossed in three hands (one is roughly contemporary to the main hand, two are later). Red rubrication, and text on the flesh side only.
  Provenance: Formerly e.44.
- Two leaves from a music book with musical notation., Fourteenth century.; Size: 1: 332 x 234 mm (252 x 190 mm) Four staves: 21.5 mm. 2: 331 x 232 mm (251 x 191 mm). Four staves: 21.5 mm. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Description: Two leaves from a music manuscript, written in Latin on parchment with square notation and red, four line staves in a Southern Textualis (Rotunda) script. Decorative capitals in red and blue ink with pen flourishes. Leaf 2 has 18cm slice in the vellum which has been stitched together, thread remains intact.
  Provenance: Formerly 11.1-2.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_076_004.jpg (1a); CornellMedMS_076_003.jpg (1b); CornellMedMS_076_001.jpg (2a); CornellMedMS_076_002.jpg (2b).
- Leaf on vellum from a breviary, Flanders., Circa 1350.; Size: 140 x 100 mm (95 x 70 mm). (Box 3, Folder 12bis)
  Description: Written in Latin on vellum in Gothic script, with three decorated initials. Rubricated; decorated with pen flourishes and gold leaf.
- Leaf from an Antiphonal with historiated “A” initial of a female saint preaching, from Italy., Mid-fourteenth century, ca. 1350.; Size: 481 x 355 mm (363 x 256 mm) Four staves: 27.9 mm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Description: Written in Latin in a Textualis Formata (Rotunda) script on parchment. From north-central Italy, probably in the vicinity of Bologna. Seven four line staves in red (28mm) with square musical notation. Smaller initials in alternating red and blue ink with pen flourishes. Large initial “A” measuring 9.8 x 9cm, illustrating the verse “Adaperiat dominus cor vestrum” (2 Macc. 4: “[God] open your hearts in his law and commandments, and send you peace”), the first response from the first nocturne of the first Sunday in October. Rather than referencing the Maccabees text, an epistle of the Jews in Jerusalem to those in Egypt, the miniature illustrates a scene seldom found in manuscript art: a female saint preaching to a group of men and women. In the upper compartment the gesticulating saint addresses a divided group of five men and four women, all dressed in secular garb. The palette is Bolognese. Square notation and text of later date added in the bottom margin of the verso.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 19.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_061_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_061_002.jpg (b).
- Single folio on vellum from a Decorative Breviary, from Flanders., Mid-fourteenth century, ca. 1350.; Size: 139 x 100 mm (96 x 59 mm). (Box 1, Folder 6 bis)
  Description: Decoration: one two-line multicolored initial D on colored grounds with gold highlights and a bar border extending five lines above and below into the lower margin; three multi-line alternating red and blue initials with contrasting pen work, one (on the verso) having a red and blue marginal extension the entire length of the text-block. Also, a drawing representing a dragon, added later. Text: this leaf comes the Christmas season, the end of the service for St. Stephen Protomartyr (26 December) and the beginning of St. John the Evangelist (27 December), ending just after the first lesson.
- Illuminated leaf from "Les Grandes Chroniques royales" Compostela, Paris, France, ca. 1350-1375; Size: 446 x 330 mm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Description: Decoration: Tempera and gold leaf on parchment (min., 112 x 91 mm.) Text: Includes the opening of Book IV, chapter 1, of the Grandes Chroniques de France, a royal compilation of the history of France from its Trojan origins up to, in its final form with its continuations, the death of King Charles VII in 1461. Originally drafted and updated by the monks of the royal abbey of Saint-Denis, the vernacular text provided the "official" history of the French kings, but the present miniature is also related to Spain, crusades, and pilgrimages. Charlemagne stands crowned, accompanied by two of his courtiers/preux compagnons, as San Iago/Iacobus [di Compostella] appears to him in a vision. The saint is identified by his pilgrim staff, pack, book, and his hat (subsequent pilgrims to Compostela would dress like him for centuries). According to the Chronicle of Turpin and subsequent imitations, Sant Iago instructed Charlemagne (in a [day?] dream) to come to Galicia following the Milky Way (Campus Stellae) and wrest Spain from the Saracens. The text in French in this manuscript is approximately the same, although St. James also urges Charlemagne to go to Galilee and deliver the Holy Sites.
  Provenance: Acquired by Laurent Ferri in July 2016.
- Bronze seal matrix from England., Fourteenth century.; Size: 20 mm high x 17 mm across the face; 8.2 grams. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Description: A single matrix cast in bronze. A cast stamp seal matrix with hexagonal-section shaft terminating in a pierced quatrefoil knob. The design features and Agnus Dei with a large flag on an extended Crucifix, surrounded by the legend ECCE AGNVS DEI (‘Behold the Lamb of God’). Slight corrosion below the lamb.
  Provenance: Found by metal detector in England (undisclosed location), the property of a London collector and by descent. Acquired in January 2014 by Laurent Ferri.
- Fragment of a border (9.1) and a cut-out initial “M” (9.2) from a choir book, from Italy., Fourteenth century.; Size: 9.1: 198 x 32 mm. 9.2: 200/158 x 121 mm (93 x 111 mm). (Box 1, Folder 9.1 and 9.2)
  Description: 9.1: A fragment of border decoration (20 x 4cm) with blue, tan, and mauve acanthus leaves, gold dots, and an egret-like bird. 9.2: The initial “M” on the verso painted in tan on a blue field and decorated with red, mauve, and blue acanthus leaves was cut from a fourteenth-century Italian choir book on parchment. The recto side of the fragment contains square musical notation written on red staff lines with Gothic text. 9.1 and 9.2 possibly cut from the same volume.
  Provenance: Formerly Calkins no. 25; De Ricci, II, 1237; folder 9.1-2. Obtained circa 1895 by A. D. White in Europe.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_069_001.jpg (9.1a); CornellMedMS_068_001.jpg (9.2a); CornellMedMS_068_002.jpg (9.2b).
- Leaf from a hymnal with musical notation., Fourteenth to fifteenth century.; Size: 377 x 269 mm (295 x 174 mm). Four line staves: 9.5 mm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a high-grade Textualis Formata (Textus Quadratus) hand, with square musical notation on red, 4-line staves. Including alternating red, blue, and black capitals with pen flourishes on the black initials. Taken from a binding.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 1.
- Two leaves from a legal document., Late fourteenth to fifteenth century.; Size: Folio 1: 302 x 195 mm (264 x 167 mm). Folio 2: 332 x 194 mm (264 x 169 mm). (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in four different hands in a Cursiva script. Folio 1 contains four paragraphs, each in a different hand (hands 1-4). Folio 2 written entirely by hand 4. Each leaf has writing only on the flesh side. Probably taken from a binding.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 57.1.
- Leaf from Thomas of Breslau's "Practica Medicinalis", circa 1380; Size: 10 1/2 X 13'' (267 x 330 mm) (Box 3, Folder 13b)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment, with two columns of text, mostly concerned with the different types of fevers and their remedies. An entire passage is borrowed from Spanish Arnaldus de Villanova (1240-1311), who taught for many years at the university of Montpellier. Thomas was himself a former student of medicine in Montpellier and Bologna who became bishop of Wrocław in 1270.
  Provenance: The manuscript fragment was used as a binding in the 16th century.
- One bifolium containing Avicenna’s Liber Canonis I., Late fourteenth to fifteenth century.; Size: 318 x 236/464 mm (269 x 175 mm). (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Semitextualis Libraria script. In two ruled columns and later marginal notes added. Rubrication in red ink, and red and blue initials with pen flourishes. Two rectangles have been cut from the center of each leaf approximately 90 x 10 mm in size.
  Provenance: Formerly j.28.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_080_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_080_002.jpg (b); CornellMedMS_080_003.jpg (c); CornellMedMS_080_004.jpg (d).
- Twenty three fragments recovered from binding containing sermons by Jacques de Lausanne (d. 1321), for Sundays following the Feast of Trinity., Fourteenth to fifteenth century.; Size: All approximately 212 x 141 mm (161 x 111 mm). (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Description: Written in Latin in two columns on parchment in a Textualis Libraria script. Some red and decorated capitals and red underlining.
  Provenance: Restored and donated by Mrs Fleda Meyers. Lost description by Lynn Laufenberg, 1986. Formerly folder 51.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_018_043.jpg (1a); CornellMedMS_018_044.jpg (1b); CornellMedMS_018_001.jpg (2a); CornellMedMS_018_002.jpg (2b); CornellMedMS_018_003.jpg (3a); CornellMedMS_018_004.jpg (3b); CornellMedMS_018_005.jpg (4a); CornellMedMS_018_006.jpg (4b); CornellMedMS_018_007.jpg (5a); CornellMedMS_018_008.jpg (5b); CornellMedMS_018_009.jpg (6a); CornellMedMS_018_010.jpg (6b); CornellMedMS_018_012.jpg (7a); CornellMedMS_018_011.jpg (7b); CornellMedMS_018_013.jpg (8a); CornellMedMS_018_014.jpg (8b); CornellMedMS_018_015.jpg (9a); CornellMedMS_018_016.jpg (9b); CornellMedMS_018_017.jpg (10a); CornellMedMS_018_018.jpg (10b); CornellMedMS_018_020.jpg (11a); CornellMedMS_018_019.jpg (11b); CornellMedMS_018_021.jpg (12a); CornellMedMS_018_022.jpg (12b); CornellMedMS_018_023.jpg (13a); CornellMedMS_018_024.jpg (13b); CornellMedMS_018_025.jpg (14a); CornellMedMS_018_026.jpg (15a); CornellMedMS_018_027.jpg (16a); CornellMedMS_018_028.jpg (16b); CornellMedMS_018_029.jpg (17a); CornellMedMS_018_030.jpg (17b); CornellMedMS_018_031.jpg (18a); CornellMedMS_018_032.jpg (18b); CornellMedMS_018_033.jpg (19a); CornellMedMS_018_034.jpg (19b); CornellMedMS_018_035.jpg (20a); CornellMedMS_018_036.jpg (20b); CornellMedMS_018_037.jpg (21a); CornellMedMS_018_038.jpg (21b); CornellMedMS_018_039.jpg (22a); CornellMedMS_018_040.jpg (22b); CornellMedMS_018_041.jpg (23a); CornellMedMS_018_042.jpg (23b).
- One leaf from Titus Livius, Historiae (Book 3.4-7)., Late fourteenth to fifteenth century.; Size: 334 x 210 mm (216 x 151 mm). (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Semitextualis script. Removed from the binding of a book.
  Provenance: Received President White Library, 1891. Lost description by M. Malamud, n.d. Formerly folder u.39.
- One leaf possibly from an illuminated Psalter including Psalm 19 and decorative line fillers., Late fourteenth to early fifteenth century.; Size: 263 x 173 mm (185 x 128 mm) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Northern Textualis Formata (Textus Rotundus). Decorated initials in red, blue, and gold, and unusually ornate line fillers in red, blue and gold.
  Provenance: From the Ferrini collection. Formerly folder 65.
- Richard of Middleton, commentary on the Sentences of Peter Lombard with a remark on werewolves. The note at the foot of the text on one leaf contains a quote from Pliny to the effect that no absurdity lacks witnesses among the Greeks (from a passage in the Historia naturalis, book 8 cap. xxii, where he explains the notion of lycanthropy)., Circa 1400, Italy.; Size: 2 fragments, 152 x 100 mm and 154 x 98 mm (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a round Gothic, with a note in Humanistic italic minuscule at foot of text on one leaf. Remains of 18-19 lines, roughly half a column of text each from a quarto page with double columns. One initial in red, and rubrication in red and blue. Leaves are very worn (possibly water damaged) with some loss of text.
  Provenance:
- One bifolium from statute book of a city in Northern Italy, possibly Lucca., Fifteenth century.; Size: 350 x 510/262 mm (226 x 145mm). (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Southern Textualis Formata (Rotunda) script. First folio contains a few late and illegible scrawls and the words “No. 114. The second folio (recto and verso) is a fragment of a law-book/ body of statutes, probably from Lucca. There is some marginal glossing, and the verso contains a red initial and rubric that reads: “viij. De termino instantie cause principalis”.
  Provenance: Brought in Lucca, Italy, by George Burr for the President White Library. Formerly 13.2.
- One bifolium probably from Aristotle’s Metaphysics, from England., Fifteenth century.; Size: 226 x 315/162 mm (213 x 145 mm) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a late Textualis Currens script with Secretary influences, highly abbreviated. Containing Tractatus Philosophus. Lower and upper part of leaves have been damaged, some partial stains, and some rubbing of text on inner folios.
  Provenance: Gift of George Tyler, ’28. Formerly folder 67.
- Leaf from Lauda (song) book, from Italy., Early fifteenth-century.; Size: 214 x 147mm (146 x 90 mm). (Box 4, Folder 1)